Is French the number one language here?
>> They ran salty and settled this valley
here. A
>> place very few know about in the rest of
the country. What's going on in
Madawaska? Smoke stack. That's Canada.
Did you build this place?
>> I did.
>> No electricity.
>> This is 96.
>> Well, that's where we are in Maine.
>> Now, this building looks straight out of
the Soviet Union.
>> Here you go, son.
>> Thank you.
>> There's a lot of rice and a lot of pork
in there.
>> Oh, this is cool. Didn't think I'd see
something so grand up here.
>> Stay a while. Maybe you'll change your
mind.
>> That is actually the Acadian flag. It's
as basic as you can get it.
>> There's a moose tooth. Towns like this,
if the main employer goes, it really
hurts them. It's a different country.
>> Absolutely.
>> Which as a traveler is what you want.
It's interesting. Let's cruise around a
bit and then hit the road.
Good morning, guys. Here we are in the
far northern tip of Maine, Canada, just
a couple of miles away. And now, when
most people from the outside think of
Maine, they're thinking lobster. They're
thinking a beautiful coastline. They're
thinking summer vacation.
But up here is a completely different
world. It's got a frontier feeling to
it. It has French and Aadian culture
that's come over for hundreds of years
and influenced the culture. So today
we're going to hit the road. We're going
to run the border here for most of the
day, pop into these small towns, talk to
the locals, get into a world that is
well very different from the rest of the
state, and I'd say a surprise, a place
very few know about in the rest of the
country. Let's do this.
Okay, here we are at the Luring Air
Force Base, built after World War II.
Construction began in 1947. So, it's
this huge facility I want to show you
guys just because it's so interesting.
Like, it's one of these former Cold War
bases set up for the big threat, the
Soviet Union. And they chose this
location because it's the closest
location to Europe from the mainland.
Oh, that is so awesome. Look at this
hanger.
At the time, this was one of the biggest
hangers in the world. And this base was
meant to hold 100 B36
Peacemaker bombers, the predecessor to
the B-52. So, there were B-52s out here
afterwards. And you can see right now
this is being used. I guess they're
refitting a plane or doing something in
there. So, it's been sold off. I don't
know who owns it now, but there's
obviously something still happening
around here. There are all these roads
really well set up for the place to be
pretty much self- sustaining. Schools, a
church, bowling alley, stores,
housing. From 47 to 90, I believe right
around 92 or so, place was thriving.
And then when the government
pulled the plug, things changed
economically in this region big time.
people moved out. The money that this
base was generating well all went away.
The railway came in here and this was
one of the snow plowers
and so
Oh, this is cool. Look at this old guy
here.
Just imagine the snows came in brutally
frigid winters
and they needed to keep the tracks
clear. And so
you can see the tracks are grown over
there. Nature is taking this place back
fully. Let's cruise around a bit and
then
hit the road.
You can see all the roads are named
after states. Pennsylvania, Alabama,
Georgia,
and there are just a ton of roads like
this going off forever. wide, well set
up when this was a totally functioning
town. Basically a company town. The
company being the US military and
everyone employed through them. What's
that? Education center. So I'm guessing
that's a school. Pretty big place. Look
at that. And then it looks like the
solar panels have come in.
I'm guessing this is where a lot of
people lived or they were developing it
for more service members to move in. But
you got all these roads, you got the
utilities, you got the sidewalks, even
barely see them through the grass.
Roughly 22,000 people left the area.
Almost 10,000 direct and indirect jobs.
Now, this building looks straight out of
the Soviet Union. That's as union as it
gets. That could be Duchon Bay Tigstan
or Novi Sibero
Ukraine. I mean that's Soviet for those
that don't know.
You can barely read out the letters
here. Loring Health Center. Actually
quite nice. And look at this. nature
just poking right back through the
ashalt
like it's nothing. You got these old
curbs in here. You know, people were
walking in for their health
appointments,
coming into the health center for
checkups. I'm sure basic procedures,
maybe some surgeries.
And then right next to it, the luring
chapel. That's interesting. They're
connected. Huh. Never seen that before.
That is wild.
And so you could go pray in here.
You know, I might have said '92 before,
but it was 94 when it closed down. So
the Cold War stopped in '91.
US government realized they didn't need
all these operations. They're very
expensive to maintain. So they closed
down a lot of these. Not a lot. I
believe a few Air Force bases with this
sole purpose in mind to pay attention to
the Soviet theater. You know, this is
the closest way, I'd say, outside of
Alaska to get over the the North Pole or
the Arctic flight path where Russia
really isn't that far away. And so they
deemed this unnecessary because the
threat was over and both countries
backed off at that time.
And you see in here, I mean, it wasn't
that long ago. 94, what are we talking
32 years? I wonder what they'll do with
these. If there's any use down the road
now, there's some buildings out here I
can see with cars out front. Anyone who
knows what's going on here from the
area, please chime in on the comments.
That would be great because it was hard
to find out what's really going on here
at this very point in time.
Here
we are in Van Beern. We are right on the
border now and this place seems to be in
flux. We've got a Renault happening.
Museum, movie theater. How you doing,
sir?
>> Good morning.
>> You from Van Beern?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> How is it these days?
>> It seems to be getting better. getting
better. You got a renovation going on
here.
>> Yeah, they're going to have several
businesses here and there's another
business opening up down the street.
>> Is French the number one language here
>> right now? It's the number two cuz it's
turning more and more English.
>> It's turning more English.
>> Don't want to cut French.
>> Did you grow up speaking French or
English?
>> Yes, French.
>> French?
>> Yes.
>> You're a Canadian?
>> Yeah. Can't see it. Do it.
>> The Cajun story is all about you guys.
>> I know. I know. My ancestors coming from
Canada. Then before that, France and
that.
>> Okay. Okay. So, when the British burned
down their villages in Nova Scotia,
that's when they got out of Nova Scotia.
>> Yeah. Some of us moved to New Brunswick
here. Short period of time.
>> Yeah.
>> Then we moved over here and some of them
moved to Louisiana. It's kind of was
like a separation, I think.
>> And so,
>> then they call it persecution. I don't
know if they call it today.
>> But town's coming around, you're saying?
>> Yes. It used to be better than that when
the base was open. This was hopping. But
>> this place was when was it hopping?
>> When the base was open, Lauren. Oh, this
place was busy.
>> I was just that Lauren. Yeah, this place
was busy.
>> I read this is the one town where
McDonald's is shut down because of lack
of
>> bankruptcy
>> from bankruptcy
>> and it happens to be where the town
office is down.
>> It's down here
>> about a mile down the street.
>> Thank you. Take care, sir.
>> You too. Yeah, it's so interesting. So
guys of that generation, I think most of
them French was the native tongue. And
you can hear he has an accent in
English.
That's real lighting.
>> That's real light.
>> Oh, wow.
>> That's how they used to bring the kids
to school back in the day.
>> No way. That was the school bus.
>> Yeah, it was years ago. Yeah.
>> What a cool place to live, huh?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Okay. So, when you ladies get together,
you might speak French, you might
respond in English, vice versa.
>> We We're do we do we do French.
>> A little bit of French, a little bit of
English. That's the French Canadian of
us. That That's where we get it. Okay.
>> The Parisian French.
>> Okay.
>> You know, so it's it's it's that French
English dialect.
>> Do people up here feel removed almost
from the rest of the country? Cuz you're
living in your own world.
>> Well, they have to answer that. I've
been going from here for 40 years.
>> Okay. You guys do.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> You feel removed
>> and uh
>> even for even from the rest of Maine.
>> Mhm.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. And we're still coming
>> cuz I live in Connecticut for 10 years
and I when we came back my husband and I
>> and I don't think I could ever move.
>> You're loving it up there.
>> I love it up here.
>> Arusta County
>> called the county. That's called the
county.
>> I read bigger than Connecticut and Rhode
Island in one county.
>> They've also said a lot of times whether
they're politicians or not that the
state of Maine is kind of divided into
two sections. There's Maine, southern
Maine, and then there's the county.
>> I think they'd like to sell the county.
>> They want to sell the county. What? To
Canada?
>> You guys go back and forth a bunch over
the border.
>> We do.
>> We Well, I don't because I I live in
southern Maine. But it's funny because
when I left Tuesday to come down, the
first thing I said is, "Okay, I think I
said to my husband, I I need to bring my
passport because what if she wants to go
to Canada? I I tucked my passport in
because we need passports now. Now when
we all grew up there was no such thing.
>> You just went over walk across drive
across. I went in a Volkswagen beetle
with 11 of us.
>> Oh, in a 11 in a beetle.
>> We were all stacked on one on top of the
other. I was in high school. Hey, we
were just stacked up. So when we get to
the customs, they usually say bring
anything. They make us all get out. So
now, how are we going to get back in?
>> Back in and fit all in.
>> And fit all in. Yeah.
>> So September 11th changed that.
>> Yes.
>> I think that's what that's when it
started.
>> I think so. So you you ladies are having
a lot of fun.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Is that
>> we enjoy getting That's a fair
assessment.
>> Well, these are my in-laws. They're
ex-in-laws, but they're my best friends.
And then this is my best friend, too.
They're all from This is They're all
related, right?
>> Okay.
>> Well, and
you got Exactly.
All right, just want to show you where
we're at here in Van Beern. But if you
go right over the river, that is Canada.
So the goal is to we started down there
and we're just tracing the St. John's
River. Going to go to Madawaska.
If we have time, get over into Canada
actually and then keep following this
area. So when you back out, that's where
we are in Maine. And this part in the
far north is where that Acadian culture
is. And it feels totally different,
which as a traveler is what you want.
It's interesting. And I love these
borderlands. I love these, hey, I have
family on that side of the border and
they have family here. Both sides are
connected, right? And they're there's a
different language at play. It's just
like the southern border. It's just like
in the south of Texas or Arizona, a lot
of families on both sides, more Spanish
being spoken. And then here it's French.
You know, it's a lesser story. Not many
people, I don't think, know about this
story. Look at that house. That is
awesome. Some old beauties here.
I guess this is it. The old McDonald's.
It's the town office now.
There we go. There's a destruction
village.
This looks nice.
Historical site.
Okay, ladies. So, we're going to cruise
in a golf cart, right?
>> Absolutely.
>> But you're saying you'd rather me drive?
>> Go ahead.
>> Okay. Okay.
She's pretty good, though. Look at that
pedal to the metal.
>> Oh, I'll turn it around.
All right. And then if you want, you
know how to do that, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'll I'll drive it. Thanks,
Holly.
>> You're welcome.
>> And your name?
>> I'm Julie.
>> Julie. Okay. Julie, let's do it.
>> Have fun.
>> Thank you.
>> Walkie-talkie.
>> Yeah. This Oh, there we go.
>> Yeah, it's a bit temperamental.
>> Touchy.
>> Okay, Julie. This is awesome. Old school
Acadian Village, correct?
>> Yes. There are four buildings that are
original. They were all moved from
different locations cuz originally this
was farmland.
>> Okay. So, to get this straight, I think
I got it down pretty well. Acadians
originally from France.
>> Yep.
>> Mostly Nova Scotia. Brits and French
fought it out. Brits won.
>> They said to the Acadians, "Show
allegiance to the crown."
>> Yep.
>> The Acadians were like, "No, we're not
doing that." And then the Brits burned
down their villages.
>> Yeah, they were deported in two
different waves. So it originally
started with the great deportation. So a
lot of them um passed off and they were
deported in like what the first wave was
where a lot of them came and settled in
Maine PEI and Nova Scotia. So they came
along the area. Now after that I guess
the British came in and kind of wanted
to see if some of them wanted to come
back to where they originally were and a
lot of them didn't. So they were
deported in the second wave where many
of them ended up coming and um located
here along the St. John Valley
>> and then some of them continued on to
Louisiana where the Acadians there
turned into being known as the Cinjun,
>> right? And it's just a slur of the word.
It means Acadian, but they just started
saying Cajun
>> and they were in the swamps because they
are free there. They could speak French
easily because it was it was French
territory at the time.
>> Yes. So it wasn't like a big change. And
then they were out there with natives
and blacks seeking refugee from slavery.
So it like developed this really
interesting culture and food and style
and like it's a really interesting mix
>> cuz I mean there was at least over
10,000 Acadians that were forced off of
their land and a lot of them were
separated where they never got to meet
up with their families again.
>> And then your flag here, it's like a
French flag with a yellow star.
>> That is actually the Acadian flag. It
does have the French colors because
obviously they were from France. So they
did have the same descendant. But the
yellow star represents our lady of the
assumption. She is the patron saint of
Acadia which is where they came from. So
her star on that flag represents her
patronage and represents the Acadians.
This is the oldest house on site as well
as in the state of Maine
>> before the Brits were torching them.
>> This is what the Acadians were living
in.
>> Yeah. This one's 1700. So, it's as basic
as you can get it. Watch your head.
>> Watch my Okay. They were short people.
>> Yes.
>> Wow.
>> That's one thing that you'll notice in a
lot of the buildings is that they were a
lot shorter. So, that means that
everything else was built.
>> Check that out. They were like hobbits,
huh?
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's a nice way of putting
it. If you look over at the door,
there's a crucifix.
>> So, the Acadians, they were very strong
in their beliefs. Again, the whole
reason why they left Britain in the
first place was because they were not
allowed to practice the way they wanted.
>> They were Catholic, right?
>> Yes. So, a lot of the places here you'll
have either it's Jesus or it's Mary or
it's a crucifix or it's a nod to their
religion. So, this home originally does
have the dirt floor. It keeps it cool in
the summer, but it does the same thing
in the winter.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Any animals that they had, they would
bring them all in and use that to help
provide heat. They would bring pigs and
whatever else in here.
>> If it was something that could if it was
an animal that they had and it could
help provide any kind of heat in the
winter time, they used it. Their parents
would sleep here and then you would have
the youngest child or the baby depending
on would be in a bassinet underneath and
then all the other children would sleep
upstairs in the loft area.
>> Okay. How many children typically?
>> Um well, we have other houses on site
that have shown that they've had
families up to about like 18. So, they
did have bigger families. They did not
have a specific amount of how many were
in this specific home, but they were
common to have like more than like 10.
>> How does a woman have 18 kids?
>> Well, some of the times they would
either be sets of twins. Twins were more
common or if they'd have like I don't
know about triplets, but they would have
more.
>> That was just a full-time job.
>> But then again, at the same time, with
all the epidemic and all the different
viruses and diseases, having them is one
thing, but would they live to adulthood?
A lot of them would die at infancy or
they would only be a year or two old
before something would happen.
>> Okay. So, that time isn't correct.
>> No, you're an hour.
>> It's correct. If you're across the
river,
>> I'm getting a Canadian signal.
>> Yeah, you can if you wanted to.
>> I've never heard of Rogers.
>> That's the cell carrier in that part of
the
>> So, on this side it's 2:00, but when you
cross the border, if it still says that,
then it's correct for them.
>> Okay. I was like, I got to make a lot of
ground.
>> We'll show you the map. deportation map
is in the back.
>> Shows
>> Oh, yeah.
>> where they started off.
>> Yeah.
>> And it shows where a lot of them settled
in. So, a lot of them came and they came
down the different areas, but then a lot
of them migrated over.
>> So, they came from the different places
and where they've settled.
>> They originally came from France, then
they went back to France. And here's the
route they took to Louisiana. A lot went
there.
>> Some of them made like pit stops along
the way. It wasn't like a straight shot
from France to Louisiana. They a lot of
them were deported or had to move
multiple times before they finally were
able to settle. They said there was
close to 10,000 close to 11,000 forced
off their land.
>> But there is a good chunk of them that
also died on the ships and didn't make
it. So there are like a little piece of
that that they passed away during the
journey.
>> Well, I could spend hours here
>> when you have more down time.
>> When I have more downtime. This is
really cool.
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. You guys are
so nice.
>> Yeah, you're welcome to take this. If
you have to fold it up to get it on the
plane or
>> I might have to fold it, but
>> but that's it's yours.
>> I appreciate that, Sean.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, after your tour, you're going to
have a lineup out the door.
>> She's got a line coming right now.
>> She's great.
>> Oh, you got some coming?
>> Yeah, a couple ladies are coming in.
Perfect.
>> Hello, ladies.
>> How are you?
>> Oh, doing well. It's great in there.
>> Yeah,
>> really cool.
>> Thank you.
>> Have fun. Yeah.
>> Hello.
So, we're really close now. That's
Canada over there. Those cars on that
road, that's Canada. Just the river
separating the two countries.
So close yet so far. And then this
beauty
old church here.
But what a grand old church in the
middle of nowhere.
>> Hello.
>> How you doing, sir?
>> Pretty well. And you?
>> Doing great. This is beautiful.
>> Thank you. Didn't think I'd see
something so grand up here.
>> But it's the only church in this
village.
>> Well, this village has what, 10 people?
>> 90 right now, but it has 700.
>> Oh.
>> A century ago when this was built.
>> So cool. I love these border regions.
>> Yeah. Well, there's a river there, and
that river is 100 ft deep here. Right
here.
>> Does anyone ever swim across?
>> I did. I swam once because I had some
friends that lived in a house that you
can't see. It's buried in the trees
there. And I'm a strong swimmer, but I
came out a quarter of a mile downstream.
>> It's flowing pretty quickly.
>> It's It's a It's a swift river. They
used to float a lot of logs down the
river.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> There are some artificial islands just a
little bit under the surface that they
tied chains to to keep the logs in the
right path. Canadian logs from the
American logs.
>> Seriously?
>> Seriously. Where are you headed now?
>> Madawaska. And then I'm going over to
Canada.
>> Okay. You have a Do you have a passport?
>> Yep.
>> All set. Here
we are. Madawaska, Maine. Adawaska has a
story, that's for sure. You see all
these for sale signs.
This is cute down here. Nice little
place. How you guys doing?
>> Great.
>> I'm loving this part of Maine.
>> Stay a while.
>> Maybe you'll change your mind.
>> I'm from Pennsylvania. I moved up here 5
years ago.
>> No way.
>> I had no idea that this area was going
in the toilet very fast.
>> It's not doing well.
>> They used to have 15, 20 bars in this
town. There's not a bar anymore. They
used to have a Kmart. Kmart's gone. They
used to have a McDonald's. McDonald's is
gone. That store is closing. Uh, if you
go to Fort Kent, two out of every three
stores are closed now.
>> What happened? The mill's still running,
right?
>> At like 30% of what they used to do.
See the Acadian flag flying on the light
posts. Here we go. Madawaska Owls, class
of 2026.
Shout out to Marcus. Good job, Marcus.
Graduated
smoke stack. That's Canada. This is the
plant still hires people. The plants
also on the other side. So on the
Canadian side, I guess they're taking
wood, making pulp, and then there's
actually a pipe that comes across the
river, and that pulp comes over here to
the American side. And on the American
side, that's where the paper is made.
And over the river here is 16,000
people. Here is roughly 4,000
people. So, a much bigger town. The
biggest thing today by far, Madawaska's
had better days. I'd say Van Beern felt
a little bit better off downtown
that first town today. So, let's check
out Madawasa first and then uh get into
Canada. I'm excited. I always love doing
the border crossings.
What's going on in Madawaska?
>> Madawaska. People are working.
>> Mill hiring a lot. They got a lot of
jobs there.
>> Maybe 5 600 jobs.
>> 5600.
>> Without the mill, we wouldn't be doing
this.
>> Okay. So, it's it's keeping the town
chugging along,
>> I guess. So,
>> all right.
>> Northern part of Maine would not exist
>> without the mill.
>> Without the mill. So if that mill closed
down, it would be like Milanino here,
right?
>> No, it would be worse. Military.
>> You gave the thumb down, sir. You if the
mill went, it would be a big problem.
>> Be a ghost town.
>> Ghost town. What? Good paying jobs
there.
>> Oh yeah. Oh yeah.
>> People make a living
>> for up here. It's good paying.
>> You can pay your mortgage, get by.
235$26
an hour.
>> All right, guys. Take care.
>> I meet a dude named Tiger. Do you guys
know Tiger?
>> Tiger Martin?
>> Yes.
>> He's actually doing some carpentry work
for us.
>> He does carpentry. Yeah.
>> Tell Tiger Travis said hi.
>> Okay, I will.
>> Yeah.
>> So, the one thing we have planned today,
guys, is meeting a guy named Tiger. And
Tiger lives up in the woods. It's going
to be our last stop. Kerosene lamps.
Really funky setup. Local legend. These
guys all know him. And Tiger's about 45
minutes from here. So, one of you guys
told me about him, so I reached out. So,
we'll end there today in this cool. I
think it's somewhat off the grid
situation with a local character. But
this gets nicer up here. There's a nice
park, kids in the playground, and if you
saw my last video on Milaninoet, that's
a story of a town where the mill shut
down, the jobs left, and it's in this
funky position. And and as the guy said
there, towns like this, of course,
there's other stuff going on, but if the
main employer goes,
it really hurts them.
Yeah, this place is quiet. It's good to
see the road work happening. When I said
Frontier Field this morning, these towns
are separated by a fair amount of space.
The camera's off most of the time,
right? And then this is the biggest
urban development we've seen so far
obviously, but it just has a feeling of
being out there. And from almost
another time,
we have a festive deck. They're trying
to Madawaska. They have these nice
flower planters up
>> all the time.
>> Oh, thank you, Annette.
>> Do you live here, Annette? I live in
Westfield, but we come up here all the
time camping.
>> We fish the river.
>> You loving it?
>> Yeah. We love it in the summer. In the
winter, we go to Florida. And we watched
one of your shows in You went to Clon,
the town near Kiston. There was a
restaurant there.
>> And we went there and I went there. Yes.
And
>> that's cool. He wanted to get I forget
what it was. Cow Stew or something.
>> Okay. So, your town is how far from
here?
>> Westfield is 70 mi from here. You know,
Prescy, you have to come through Prescy
to get here.
>> This far north, it feels almost like
it's a different country.
>> Absolutely.
>> Feels it right.
>> The people are awesome. They're
different. They talk different. They
from down from Westfield.
>> 100%.
>> Yeah.
>> Who knew that Maine was so mixed up?
Yeah,
>> I guess Maynard's dead, but I had no
clue.
>> It's really something else.
>> And you have a
>> This is Mojo.
>> Mojo.
>> Mojo. He's a cutie, huh?
>> Yeah, he's a good boy.
>> Can you please come in the house?
>> All right, guys. Just want to show you
what some of the neighborhoods look like
here in Madawaska. And once you get away
from that main drag, it actually gets a
lot better as far as the looks of
things. Like there's some nice homes,
nice gardens, lawns,
and I bet most of these incomes are
coming from the mill. I would guess.
Seems to be the only gig in town. It's
really just peaceful up here. And
everyone keeping their lawn nice and
things trimmed. And then we just hit the
end of town here. It's small.
Not every house looks like this
neighborhood, but actually quite a lot
of nice, well taken care of places.
Let's get some food. Kuon's cinjun
shack.
>> This is your setup?
>> Yes, sir. This is Kuon's cinjun shack.
>> Are you cinjun?
>> Yes, I am. I'm from a vols parish,
Louisiana. I was born in New Orleans and
then till I was about 11 and then we
moved back to Voy Parish which is more
of a Acadian uh area not far from
Lafayette.
>> And then how'd you end up here?
>> I was a bridge painter in 2003 and ended
up getting married, have kids, stayed
here uh I've been here ever since. But
>> you were painting a bridge up here?
>> Yes. There was an international bridge
that's torn down now, but 23 years ago
they had repainted it.
>> Okay. So the bridge that goes to Canada.
Yeah, I know of at least eight people
right here in town that are from
Louisiana and most of them are been here
in the last 5 or 6 years.
>> Why are they coming up, you think?
>> I don't know. I guess everybody has
their own journey. So, a lot of my
customers come here because they're from
the south and they miss a taste of the
south, you know.
>> What you got here? Two damn balls. Here
you go, sir.
>> Thank you. Walk me through what's going
on here. Okay, that is a Cajun pork butt
cooked down until it's h shredded and
then it's mixed with rice. It's chilled
and then Lily takes it and uh puts it in
some batter and some breading and we fry
it up for you. Why don't you give it a
try?
>> So, Lily, you put some time into this.
>> Yeah.
>> Lily has to make the ball from scratch
and then uh
>> it's it's like um an anchor. It's heavy.
>> Yeah, it's a lot of rice and a lot of
pork in there.
>> Okay.
>> You know, it's a meal. Uh, two meals in
a French fry for 10 bucks.
>> Lily, I'm going to have you hold this.
I'm just waiting for this thing to cool
down.
>> Yeah, it's going to be if you wait for
the reaction.
>> Oh, yeah. Look at that.
>> It's just Cajun boot. And like in
Louisiana, most places you buy balls,
they buy their bun at different butcher
shop. I make my own from scratch.
>> That is so good. Because I was thinking
it's the ones I've had have more rice
and this there's a lot of meat in this.
>> I I just do it that way because
>> that is tasty. Like I could put more
rice, but uh we decide to keep it at a
certain texture. You like it? Love it.
Very flavorful.
>> They're like my favorite things here.
>> Crazy good. Ku means ain't right. Crazy
and crazy good.
>> Mr. Joe called. Oh, you know what? I bet
you might. You've been calling.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, man. The phone's in the van. This I
was talking to this gentleman and I'm
sorry, Joe.
>> No, no, no problem there.
>> What you want? A large chicken? Two
large chickens? Get me one large chicken
with jumblaya.
>> All right.
>> And then get a small chicken with fries.
>> You don't miss a Thursday evening.
>> He comes every Thursday.
>> Oh, yeah. Every He comes more than that,
but he's definitely here every Thursday.
>> All right. So, do you have a website?
>> Facebook.
>> Or I'll just leave your address. Are you
always here?
>> Yeah, we're we're here. Uh, take a menu.
It has our address and
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Thomas Street. No, this is definitely
worth going to. 390 St. Thomas Street,
Madawaska, Maine. This is the place.
Awesome food.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you. We appreciate it.
>> All right.
>> Go Tigers.
>> Go Tigers. These are fantastic. Didn't
think I was getting a meal like that
today. So, if you're in the region in
the area, you want the real deal, I'll
have that link down below in the
description. Now, let's get gas and off
to Canada.
Full service. still exists here.
>> Yeah.
>> It's not a main thing or anything. It's
just this
>> No, just this business.
>> Just this guys. Do you charge more for
full service
>> and you do the windows and everything?
>> Windows and it's an Acadian thing. I
think
>> it's an Acadian thing. Kayen, I started
the windows. If it's part of the
service, go for it, man.
>> You guys might be the last ones left
doing this.
>> I think so.
>> Actually, I think isn't there one state
that still does this? I forget where.
>> New Jersey.
>> Is it? Okay.
They don't let you. They legally don't
let you pump your gas there
>> still.
>> Yeah.
>> But you guys have a good gas price and
then you add this service.
>> We add this service.
>> Nice.
>> So, here we go. Going to Canada.
And this is the process. Unfortunately,
it's going to be a very short trip to
Canada just to get a quick feel. We got
spikes. No reverse there. And then just
right over this bridge. Look at that. I
mean, the two are right next to each
other. Now, during the pandemic, the
border was closed, I believe, for most
people. I heard a story the other day of
someone who couldn't see his girlfriend
on the other side. I forget for how
long, but for a while. That bridge
there, that's where the pulp goes over
to the US side. Okay, so like all
borders, got to put the camera down.
Here we go.
Welcome to New Brunswick.
border experience went like this. She
just opened up and we talked restaurants
forever
as the cars just stacked up behind and
she didn't seem to care at all and she
was very friendly giving me like a
million options of where to go.
So, here we are downtown.
Here's that big church we saw from the
other side. It's a beauty. And so this
definitely is more of a city. Edmonton
Sun. Yeah, the mill is much bigger here.
Providing a lot more jobs, I believe. I
don't smell it too bad. I don't know if
it does get bad or not, but this town is
four times as big and looks like it's
definitely thriving more than Madawaska.
What's up you guys? Are you guys from
here?
>> Yeah.
>> You guys go in fighting or what?
>> Yeah, we train there. Honestly,
martial arts.
>> Martial arts?
>> Yeah.
>> Do you guys ever go to the US side?
>> Yeah, all the time.
>> Yeah. Go fuel up there cuz it's
>> You fuel up?
>> Yeah. It's way cheaper.
>> How much cheaper?
>> Like 50 45 cents cheaper outside.
>> Nice. Can I walk in with you guys?
>> Right on.
>> Okay. So, you guys go to the US for gas?
>> Yeah.
>> What else?
>> Uh, groceries, too. I buy a lot of stuff
there.
>> Groceries.
>> A lot of stuff is cheaper.
>> That's way cheaper.
>> I like going to the US.
>> All right.
>> So, this is my humble
>> Okay. So, this is your business?
>> Yeah.
>> How's it going?
>> It's pretty good. Pretty good, I would
say. Yeah.
>> Okay. Jiu-Jitsu,
>> you know, jiu-jitsu, Muay Thai, MMA.
>> MMA. Yeah.
>> It's good for your mind, isn't it?
>> It's awesome. Not just the body, but
your mind.
>> It's mostly the mind.
>> Why? You just get a release or what?
>> You get a release. Once you leave here,
you're like there's nothing on your
mind.
>> You don't want to get
>> while you're here, there's nothing on
your mind. You're not thinking about
your life problems, your boss. You know
what I mean?
>> Okay.
>> So, for a lot of people, that's why they
like it.
>> Okay. I don't want to hold you up too
long, but in Edmonson, how are things
overall? The mill pretty much keeps this
town running, right? the mill, the
hospital too, uh the school district,
but I would say it's mostly mostly the
mill.
>> Mostly the mill. Yeah. And how are
things right now?
>> I think they're pretty good. My brother
works there.
>> Cool.
>> It's an older mill. Like it's over 100
years old. You don't maintaining as much
as they should.
>> You can live a good life working at the
mill, pay your pay your mortgage, live a
life.
>> Cost of living has definitely went up
though, like dramatically.
>> Big time.
>> That's everywhere, right?
>> Yeah. It's super expensive now. Like an
apartment that used to be $600 might be
like $1,300.
>> 1300 now.
>> Okay.
>> It's It's insane.
>> Do you mind if I show them?
>> All right.
>> Please call him.
>> I'll follow you, boss.
>> It's mostly a male thing, but we have a
a brave female in here doing it. That's
awesome. How long you been doing this?
>> Um it's my second day, actually.
>> Oh, great.
>> But um I did taekwond do when I was
younger and then I wanted to uh You just
chuni. Is that what in taekwond do? I
remember that.
>> So yeah, I wanted something that kind of
resembled it a little bit. And then
>> you want to have good skills.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's great.
>> See, this guy's from the US. He crosses
over there.
>> You cross You cross for this?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, that's awesome.
>> Yep. Right across town called Madawaska.
>> I just came from there.
>> Oh, did you?
>> Yeah. Yeah, I just came over.
>> What are you doing over there?
>> I'm making a video of Northern Maine.
>> Are you?
>> And I'm like, I'll just go over the
bridge, check it out.
>> Yeah. Now I'm here and
>> there's more going on on this side than
than Madawaska.
>> Yeah, I can feel that. It's literally 2
minutes to get over here.
>> Oh yeah, you can walk. Growing up, I
used to
>> drink on the American side
>> cuz it's cheaper.
>> Okay.
>> And then there was clubs on this side.
>> So we'd either walk
>> completely across like over the bridge,
either take a taxi to the bridge or just
literally walk it.
>> So for you it's not even like another
country. It's just like your buddies and
>> it doesn't feel like another country
though.
>> It's your backyard.
>> I'll play hot.
>> Are you a Canadian?
>> Uh I'm both American and Canadian and
and I am a Canadian. Yes.
>> Cool, man.
>> I was born here on this side because my
mother is Canadian.
>> Okay.
>> So, she's able to come on this side,
have me in Canada. The hospitals are
better.
>> Okay.
>> And then because of that, my father's
American and I'm both an American and
Canadian citizen.
>> He runs a good operation, huh?
>> Yeah. Well, I'm brand new. It's my
second day.
>> Okay. It's her second day, too.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> Special salty.
>> Yeah. So, I'm I'm a new I'm a newbie
here. So, second day means it worked the
first time.
>> We're seeing you have two children.
>> Yes.
>> And this is just the ultimate release
from that.
>> Yeah.
>> It's a stress reliever.
>> Yeah. My youngest is a year and a
halfyear-old.
>> Okay.
>> And my oldest is 2 and 1/2.
>> You got your hands full?
>> Yeah. Just kind of needed something to
escape home, you know, other than work.
>> Yeah.
How is New Brunswick different from
Quebec?
>> It's not even the same people. The way
they act and talk the same. Our French
is like they call it our French is like
broken compared to theirs. So it's
really different.
>> You go for English. Is that what you
call it?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So Quebec has a different feel
than over here.
>> Oh, way different. And we're right on
the border of it.
>> Yeah. It's weird. And people usually
like
>> you can like dis distinguish. Is that
the word?
>> Yeah.
>> Like one another really.
>> You can tell immediately.
>> Like immediately just by the way they're
walking and
>> No way.
>> Yes.
>> Can you tell the Yankees look they walk
differently?
>> What's the Yankees?
>> The Americans?
>> Oh, no. No.
>> You can't tell if they're American or
not?
>> No.
>> No way. That's crazy. You can't tell if
they're American or not, but you can
tell if they're from Quebec or not.
>> 100% 100%.
>> That is wild, man.
>> Yeah. And when we go to Quebec, they the
same thing for them too. The way they
see us.
>> Take care, brother. Take care. Nice to
meet you. I want to take a picture.
Okay.
>> He's a professional, man.
>> All right, Canadian viewers, I owe you a
deep dive series of Canada. It's been on
the list for a long time. It's not
happening this year, unfortunately.
But it is on my radar. I would love to
get all over this country. It's just
massive just like the United States.
It's huge. Could spend years traveling
it, right? But going to do a dive on
some of the different provinces. New
Brunswick is new to me. I've never
experienced this. There's so much to
learn about Canada. So much. And I think
it's one of those countries like the
United States that's somewhat
misunderstood or not known so well.
There's a lot to it. I have a little
experience with Montreal and Vancouver
and that's about it. So just a couple of
these border towns. That is cool. I got
to check out that building. Let's not
get a ticket. But let's do this real
quick.
Okay. Looks like a university here.
Beautiful building. Love that. But
unfortunately, this is about it for
Canada today. Got a lot of ground to
cover. And we're meeting Tiger, the man
who lives off the grid. We got to get
there cuz he's waiting for us. That was
the only thing I had set up today. Video
like this knew where I was going as far
as what towns and whatnot. And everyone
we ran into was just a spontaneous
interaction. But Tiger is the one that
is playing and we got to see him before
a good start.
Okay, so coming into the US, way more
questions. What do you do for work? I'm
a video maker. A video maker? What else
you do for work? What were you doing in
Canada? Anyways, basic feeler questions,
right? To see if someone's lying. But
definitely a lot of questioning this
trip. So, here we are back in the US,
guys. So close in a way, in another way,
so far, but look, the cultures are I get
it. We're in a politically charged
times, but people are people. I've
always loved Canada. Always enjoyed my
time there. And it doesn't seem like
it's a problem here at all. People going
back and forth, and that's the story up
here.
All right. So, this town is Fort Kent.
There's a college here. It looks quite
nice. The surrounding area is beautiful.
But you can see today all the towns are
different, right? They all have a
different economic standing. They all
have a different look. There's a fort
over there. That's why it's named Fort
Kent, I'm guessing. So, we got what? 12
minutes until Tiger
No way.
>> Tiger,
>> you made it. You must be exhausted.
>> I made it.
>> You're up and down and all around today,
huh?
>> Up and down all around.
>> Meet in person.
>> Yeah. Thanks for doing this.
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Well, look, um, one of my followers
said, "You got to meet this guy, Tiger.
>> He's living a cool life."
>> Yeah.
>> And so, here we are, Tiger. Look at your
view.
What are you doing for work, Tiger?
>> For many years, I worked in the woods as
a logger, running a forwarder and uh at
last and lemur and skidder and taught
music for a little bit and uh do
carpentry for the most part for the past
few decades there. A few decades, two
decades. Come on in.
>> A this is cool. Did you build this
place?
>> I did. Yeah.
>> By yourself or with some friends or
>> by myself?
>> No way.
>> Does that thing work in the semi dark?
>> Needs light if you got it. I don't got
it. All I got is this.
>> Yeah, I got it, too. Okay, so you don't
you don't have electricity?
>> No.
>> No electricity?
>> No. No. It says 96.
>> No way.
>> Yeah.
>> Why'd you do that?
>> Uh just uh just to be simple, I guess. I
don't know. Kind of crazy.
>> Okay, so this is how you roll.
>> Yeah,
>> you don't want to do solar.
>> I don't have much sun here. I got a
little bit of a generator here and
there. I've tried that before with
batteries and it just ends up being
easier to just just stuff it.
>> So, does that mean early to bed at
night? Get up with the get up with the
sun. Go to bed early.
>> For 14 years, I got up at 2:00 in the
morning. No way. Oh, yeah. At 6:00.
That's what the hours are in the woods.
But there's some, you know, my ancestors
there. Arcadians right there.
>> Oh, nice.
>> That's a guy from Van Beern right there.
Roger Tibido.
>> Tibido. Such a common name, huh? Yeah.
>> You have kids?
>> I do. I have six. One on the way.
>> Seven. So, seven.
>> Yeah.
>> Same wife.
>> No. So, I was married. I was married for
25 years.
>> That guy right there, his name.
He was a logger and he got hit crushed
by logs off a trailer and he died of
what they call shabu gang green. He was
54. My age.
>> You're 54? 5? Uh, 52.
>> You're in great shape, man. 52.
>> Wow. So, you just decided you wanted to
get some land, live out in the woods,
live a simple life. Hell
>> yeah.
>> And the fam loves it. Do they love this
living?
>> They did. You know, I think as children
they liked it a lot as teenagers it was
a little bit rougher and like I was talk
speaking about my failed marriage,
whatever. You know, it was hard at
homesteading and towards the end as the
kids got older and
moved, you know, kind of got into town
or whatever. It was a factor.
>> Okay.
>> You know,
>> okay,
>> it was a factor. But, uh, there's some
more family there.
>> Look, this is what's crazy. I'm all over
the country, right? This is my full-time
job.
>> Amazing.
>> And I'm constantly discovering new
things I had no idea about. But that's
the beauty of the country. You can go to
this far corner of Maine and all of a
sudden, you get into this different
culture.
>> People are people, huh?
>> People are people. You must see a lot.
People are all
>> Yeah, most people are great,
>> you know. I don't know. Bears.
>> You bear hunt.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And moose are a big thing out here.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I just had a permit last
fall. We got a cow sleeping on it. I'll
give you some if you want some.
>> Okay. Thank you. So, this is the kitchen
setup.
>> Yeah.
>> Just gas, right?
>> It's like takazinski. Yeah.
>> And this is where I keep my journals.
>> Yeah. There you go.
>> So, do you feel like this is some sort
of antidote to the modern world a little
bit? It forces you to shut down a little
bit, keep it chill.
>> It wasn't as intentional as that. Um, my
folks had started us off like that with
an out house and no electricity and I
was kind of accustomed to it and uh I
don't know. I just uh crazy I guess or
just uh didn't need to uh watch TV. I
don't know.
>> Do you have internet up here?
>> No.
>> No internet? Wow.
>> Where is everyone right now?
>> They're mostly downstate.
>> Down state. Okay.
>> Yeah. Come on now.
I just did a a typical Acadian house
except I did three stories instead of
two,
>> right? I went to some traditional
Acadian houses today. Yeah.
>> Same shape. Yeah.
>> This is great.
>> This is where I'm parked anyway.
>> So, you do obviously all wood, firewood.
>> Yeah.
>> I did a roof on the wood mill in town
and I get some wood from that and all
the scraps from work.
>> How much wood does it take to get
through a winter?
>> I got to fill that right up.
>> You just got to fill the whole thing.
>> I just did that today. It's winter and
getting ready for winter and that's part
of it, right? Getting all your fuel.
>> Yeah.
>> You're doing mostly carpentry, right?
>> So, you're building new homes or
>> cabins, homes, barns. Got two bear skin
here.
>> What are you doing? You're just curing
them or
>> just curing them right now. Trying to
make a couple rugs.
>> So, you shoot the bear, you skin it,
carve all the meat off it.
>> Yep. Can the meat, jar the meat?
>> Can it and jar it. How is bear meat?
>> Pretty good. If you take all the fat out
of it.
>> Okay. And then moose.
>> Yeah.
>> How's that?
>> Very good. You can get a little sick of
it, you know, like anything, but I break
it in with some other stuff, you know,
cow and pig and storebought stuff, too.
You know, red hot dog. But, uh, mostly,
uh, you know, like I said, I got a cow
last year. Still eating on it and and
shared a bunch of it.
That's Nola.
So Nola, you going to butcher away?
>> Yeah. Oh, come fall. Get it back. Come
fall. I got to put her on the basher
here soon.
>> See, you're creating all your own food.
>> A lot of it.
>> Yeah.
>> That's great. You eat a lot of meat.
>> Yeah, I've garden, but you know that
takes a lot of effort time. I don't have
a lot of it. It always gets to weed and
I don't know.
>> You got goats down here. The goats are
coming up.
>> Keep going for keeping the fields
fields.
>> Okay. Yeah. They think I have food, huh?
off of it.
>> So that's I mean you're out for Kent is
a nice place. It was nice cruising
through. You're literally 12 minutes
away.
>> Yeah. Cheaters paradise.
>> Cheaters paradise.
>> Worse of both worlds,
>> right? Cuz you're like
>> there's a hospital close. There's a
university which I went to. They
>> Oh, nice.
>> my daughters went to, you know, school,
high school.
So it's a small community.
It's part of that Acadian expulsion and
they settled here, what they call Fish
River. They changed it to Fort Kent, but
uh after Governor Kent, but it was
called Fish River. Okay.
>> And our people
>> weren't getting on the boats like, "Yo,
you want us to go on the boat to get to
Louisiana? We'll be there in the
morning."
>> They didn't go. They ran Si, you know,
right? Ran through the woods. And they
came down came actually up river this
way and settled this valley here. And
here we are. Yeah. So, luck of the draw
who your ancestors were cuz you would be
in Louisiana.
>> Yeah. You asked me if I felt Cajun or
not.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, it's actually to me it's the
same people just a different migration.
The Cadians were first
>> and the Kebeekqua were just after them.
>> Yeah.
>> They didn't have the big Prince Edward
Island
expulsion,
>> right?
>> But it's the same names in the same
family. So, I mean, Acadia, you know,
Aadian is a big thing there. They make
uh signs and parties and
>> yeah,
>> you know, things like that, but you
know, at the end of the day, I just
don't
>> think, well,
>> I'm a Canadian,
>> you know, I just feel just French.
>> Gotcha. But it's, you know, the same
people. My mother's side was all
>> Tibidos and Karens. And I'm related to
everybody everybody I know
>> around here.
>> Yeah. about five generations back, six
generations back,
they're all this isn't really related.
>> So, is this area changing much?
>> We're not having like the mass
migration, right, yet
>> as in people moving in.
>> Yeah. But in since co, you know, and
since uh people,
you know, it's cheaper to buy land and a
house and um I've seen, you know, people
come and go, but there's people here
that moved here in the 60s just like us
here. You know, they were like, "Oh,
man. Back to the Landers and you can buy
uh My dad bought uh 80 acres in St.
Francis, I think, for 4,000 bucks."
>> Oh, wow.
>> You know, in the early '7s, and and live
there. So it attracts the people that
just want to get away from everything.
>> Yeah. And then they leave like like you
know I think it takes a lot to to push
through some winters here.
>> You got to deal with isolation, right?
>> Yeah. You can't just like quickly go to
Home Depot there, you know.
>> Yeah.
>> I got to walk up in the winter time, you
know, ski up, ski down.
>> Oh, really? Up the driveway. You don't
plow it.
>> No. I used to when I had my kids going
to school and stuff, you know, I'd plow
it. But hey, people would ask me, "How
long does it take you to plow that?" And
I'd be like, "Four years,
you know, I don't know how long it
takes, but but like I said, I was kind
of raised like that, so I was kind of
broke to it. It's not really very
intentional. It's just my ancestors, my
grandparents, they live like that. And
uh it just seemed easy for me to do it
as opposed to paying rent and getting a
mortgage for 30 years or you know my
brother lived on the other side of the
mountain. He had 40 acres there. He
built a house in a barn and
>> okay
>> started out his family.
Time will tell. But like I said I've had
some family strife from it you know
>> right?
>> I have had family strife from it like
being isolated being out and uh all
kinds of issues with it. But I I can't
look back. I just got to look ahead.
Time will tell if I made the right
choice. I mean,
>> it'd be tough to live in the suburbs
after this.
>> Oh, yeah. I like to piss outside.
>> It's interesting. So, your grandfather
went to World War II,
>> fought for the Americans cuz he was
American.
>> Yeah, he was.
>> But didn't speak any English. No.
>> No. I mean, he did, but uh he got better
after and they gave him his GED. But uh
he has a story, you know, he was telling
his father he wanted to go with his
brothers and go and he was too young but
he went. You know how stories get
distorted or whatever and you know what
I mean?
>> Myth flag but he he said they were
filling sandbags in Okinawa. They had he
said they had to wear big some kind of
sock cuz they're worried about snakes,
you know, but there were no snakes but
>> they just thought it was all snake
ridden over there in those islands. in
uh Marshall Islands or whatever. And he
said that he was had a shirt off with a
bunch of guys and that they were filling
sandbags making, you know, and he said
he was sitting on the sandbag and he
heard
he's like, "Do you hear that?" "Yeah, I
do hear that. What is that?" He said, "I
looked down and there was sand coming
right out of the sandbag right between
my legs."
>> Wow. you know, and he said I rolled back
and uh before you know it, there was a
guy from Frenchville Frenchville by the
name of Lamar
>> and he was on his platoon or his his
company. He said it was a little short
guy named Lamar from Frenchville.
>> Uhhuh.
>> And uh they sent him out and he got that
that sniper, that Japanese sniper. So I
was this far away from non-existing over
here.
>> Yeah. And I don't even know that he'd
ever even pictures as a farmer and a
horse logger, you know, and I I can't
imagine that that he would, you know,
rally for the United States or whatever,
but yeah, he he's a Purple Heart soldier
for World War II. my grandfather and all
five of his brothers, the Tibidos from
Vanier and they all went and all came
back and there was a lot of jobs that
were gone cuz a woman took them over you
know and was kind of like h what am I
going to do you know I can't imagine but
they had big families in my pipet he had
14 brothers and sisters two died Leger
and uh Mona died of uh polio
in the early 1900s
This is your well setup.
>> That's a hot tub.
>> Oh, nice.
>> Got a sauna in there, too. And that's
the hot tub.
>> Just warm it up in the sauna.
>> Yeah.
>> There was a fell, one of my best friends
named Ernie Ford. His father was an Em.
They lived down that way. This is what
they call Vlet Violet Settlement. And
they live down that way. And he owned
almost a mile by a mile. Okay. Had 18
children.
And uh think of someone that's poor.
Okay, picture them. Okay, that's how
poor they were.
And that's they still were able to have
two teams of horses, eight cows,
all those children, fed them all, make
cheese,
milk, you know, all their beef, and they
were dirt dirt poor, you know. And
that's how much it's $300,000 to build a
house these days. I was doing a roof the
other day in Frenchville and the woman I
could hear her in French saying to her
husband, "How come this box of nails was
$140 bucks?" And I said to her, "Uh,
when did you build this house with
them?" And she said, "191 1966."
I said, "Can you imagine building it now
if a box of nails $200?"
You know,
>> being in construction, how are the
prices right now? Still going up a lot.
>> Skyrocketing. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Plywood, insulation,
>> everything. Huh?
>> Yeah. I tend to stay away from that. I
mostly just do timber framing and rough
saw lumber from local mills. But
>> but yeah.
>> So, you're building quality stuff?
>> Old school stuff? Yeah.
>> Old school? Yeah.
>> Like your house?
>> Yeah. When I was a kid, we had that huge
barn in St. Francis. I'd go in there and
see all the barn swallows and raccoons
and all the hune beans. And at some
point I went in there as an older man
and been like, "Well, if these
uneducated farmers can build this, I can
do it, you know."
>> Yeah,
>> definite. And uh just copied them
essentially.
>> Do you do it alone or you got a crew?
>> I don't have any crew. I got one fell
named Jim that works for me. My brother
worked for me for many years. My son
Isaiah worked with me for many years.
>> All right. Do you want more business?
Yeah. Ship them out. Ship them out.
>> Do you have a website?
>> No,
>> just a phone number.
>> Just word of mouth. And
>> just word of mouth. Okay.
>> Phone.
>> I wouldn't want to leave your phone
number on the internet. I know
>> you'll get all types calling you.
>> But that's all uh main there that goes
out towards uh
>> it's where I came from.
>> Yeah. Cross lake that way. That way more
is towards Frenchville. But this side
right here is where it divides and
that's Canada there.
You can't plant your garden until like
the second week of June because you'll
get a frost guaranteed. And then in
August, as soon as you see golden rod
out, you got about 6 to 8 weeks before
your your first frost. So when I first
started working in the woods or my
friend Bart Plord was being a forester
in the woods, he's like, "I can't do it.
There's no way. There's no way. The bugs
are too bad. I'll never be able to do
it." But towards early July, they slow
down. The nights are cooler. They'll
light on you and bother you, but they
won't attack you.
>> Yeah, they're not really biting. In my
machine, I used to keep a birch bar,
light that on, light that, and put deep
right on around my my boot like that cuz
they climb up your pants, even inside
the machine, you know. But around July,
I find they stop. But I tell you, Pete,
the the past five, six years, like
summer gets extended. So, you'll have
September be like August. August is like
July, July is like June. It's just kind
of pushed. I call it carpenters's dream.
You can get one more job in before it
gets too bad. But, uh,
>> is this spring coming later or is it
spring coming at the same time?
>> Past few years, I always tell everyone,
second week of May, you're not going to
have any snow. It'll disappear, but it
doesn't feel like it.
>> So, you have you have snow here until
the second week of May.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> And then when's the first frost come?
Usually
>> late August.
>> Oh, wow.
>> Yeah. So really,
>> it's zone one for planting.
>> Really short growing season.
>> Yeah. You got to savor it. You got to
savor their summers,
>> which is like two months.
>> Go canoeing, fishing. Get out, you know.
Oh, I'm just going to go to bed. Nope.
I'm going to first leg wer I'm going to
You got to go. You got to go enjoy it,
you know, while you can. Cuz like I
said, there's two seasons up here.
Winter and getting ready for winter. you
know, skiing and bad skiing.
>> Your wife's brother is a twin.
>> Okay.
>> We just lost him uh maybe two days ago.
>> Oh, man. I'm sorry.
>> Thank you. He was killed in the a car
accident in the middle of the night.
>> Oh, man.
>> And
life's not going to be the same for her.
He was saying, you know, I'll I've never
existed without him, you know. Oh man,
>> she's pretty vacant right now. She was
going to be here, but she's so, you
know, like I can't.
>> Yeah, understandable.
>> You know, but you should have seen all
the people brought them food and came by
and said heartfelt things and um
you know, which isn't easy for a lot of
people to do, say heartfelt things, you
know,
>> right?
>> But uh I have seen a lot of generosity
and a lot of uh well, I'll tell you a
story. I had just moved on here, bought
it with a little bit of money down, and
I didn't have any uh Thanksgiving dinner
with two kids and uh my wife. And I
said, "Well, I'm going to go hunting.
You know, I'll go partridge hunting and
get some partridge for Thanksgiving."
And I went all the way out back towards
my brothers and down around and all I
seen was a black weasel. I like, "Well,
I can't bring a black weasel home for
Thanksgiving." And I came home and
as you can imagine defeated and not
really providing and uh I opened up the
door and I could smell turkey or like a
a meal.
>> Yeah.
>> I was like, "What's that? How'd you get
that? Where?" And she was cooking a
turkey and apple pie and it was snowing.
You know, it was snow then and and I
said, "How'd you get that?" She said,
"Norman Levak brought that over." Norman
Levak fig he said he figured you didn't
have that starting out right here. any
game brought that for me.
>> It still rolls like that up here.
>> That's great.
>> Yeah.
I was writing down some for Oh, nice.
But the baseball tuni, a lot of
cinjunian
stuff is in that tuning.
I find that cinjun ones,
they got that vibe to it, you know.
But us is more in that
We will use those tunings.
That's K.
But around here, we're more like
Heat. Heat.
like that.
>> Nice.
>> You know,
>> that was so good.
>> That's a old tune that's called.
>> You're playing somewhere cuz I see the
dollar bills. Where do you play?
>> I play at a brewery. Play down state
sometimes.
>> Brewery where?
>> It's called First Mile. It's on Market
Street.
>> Fort Kent.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> I'll play there.
>> So people can find you there.
>> Yeah.
>> Go down to uh Benton near Waterville.
Play down there. Yeah. The Benton
Mountain Fiddle Festival there. And just
mostly some dive bars or whatever.
>> And that's just passed through the
generations.
>> Yeah. Had an uncle named Romeo.
uh Tibet who played and I grew up. It
was gone, Peter. It was gone, but there
was a whiff in the air.
>> It was still there. Oh, we used to take
all the furniture out and put it on the
porch and we'd all dance, you know, and
all night.
And I was like, well, why don't we do
that anymore? We're just watching TV in
the background and eating tortilla, you
know. So, I kind of learned myself how
to do it.
You're having another kid?
>> Yeah. I had one with Elizabeth that
passed away um at I don't know 3 4
months. And then I got her pregnant
again. This one's sticking. And uh I
like to bike my days off there. I like
to go on tracks there like with the
stupid shoes and the pants there. You
know what I mean? and and like to play
music. And I know from having six kids
by 33
that those times are more few and far
between. My brother Josh, he has nine,
okay? And he's not a Mormon or nothing
or whatever, but he's got nine.
And uh we built these houses here, okay?
He said, "Do you notice in the houses we
built don't have doors?"
And I was like,
Yeah,
didn't put any doors except the bathroom
and there's a reason for that, you know,
kind of open and inclusive. And I mean,
not that they had privacy there, you
know, not like a giant commun, okay, but
just didn't have doors and uh
they had partitions or whatever, but he
was saying, you know, there's a reason
for that. And he said, "Uh, yeah, do you
ever notice that we got big families?" I
said, "Yeah, I noticed." And I said, "I
don't know why I'm so family driven
instead of just whatever, you know." And
he said, "I feel the urge to run away
all the time. I feel the urge to go and
my wife Nina needs me, but I just want
to go, you know, and and he said,
"By yourself, you can always flee. by
yourself, you can always go be faster.
Uh but with a family, you can go
further.
And uh
and he's right. Every
father feels like that. Like it gets
crazy in the house. It's like I got to
get the out of here, you know? Or I've
heard women say, you could have found my
checkbook, I was I'm gone. You know, but
obviously you don't do it. But it's just
like stress just like jobs you've had or
whatever. It's like, "Oh yeah, you know,
you kidding me?" You know, it just gets
gets kind of crazy. But I I've seen a
lot of death in the woods and I've seen
a lot of death as uh I just spoke of the
Liz Liz's brother Pike and I've done CPR
on a kid one time. His spinal fluid was
coming out of my nose. you know, I I
just
take freedoms from myself and and I
don't live like there's no tomorrow or
whatever, you know, but it's just this
is what we got here. And like you,
you're making the most of it, you know?
You could be bagging groceries or
drinking yourself to death or no
responsibilities,
but uh
I don't know. Well, I'm not preaching
that whatever, but I I I find, like I
said, my bed had 14 brothers and
sisters. You think the his parents could
quietly make love on a Wednesday night?
You know what I mean?
>> They did it 14 times. That's
>> 14 times. And but just do it. I don't
know. I I just, you know, I there was a
time I I told you I was teaching for
about 8 years and someone asked me like,
"How can you come out of the woods for
almost 20 years and and be a teacher?"
And I was like, "Well, I just didn't
want to
live my life saying, "Boy, Tiger, he
could pile wood,
you know. I just And there's nothing
wrong with that. My son's an awesome
Ford operator. Most of my best friends
are are loggers and and they're really
raising families and, you know, it makes
purpose for it. But I'm just saying like
you're like you alluded to Peter, you're
making an impact, you know, best you
can. Can't live just live for ourselves.
Tiger's saying he can't let me go
without him giving me something.
Just a couple momentos. All right.
There's a moose tooth. Oh,
>> you could probably bring that on uh
>> on uh the flight. And uh this a maple
tap.
>> Oh, thank you.
>> Here's one of my great grandmother's
marbles.
>> Oh, you're a tiger. Tiger. Come on. Come
on.
>> Come on. Come on, brother.
>> You got a bunch of marbles. I got a
bunch of them. Don't worry.
>> Thank you. Thank you. All I got is a
hat. Can I give you a hat?
>> Yeah, give me a hat.
>> I don't have anything special. I don't
travel with
>> you. a bike trip or something.
>> Oh, that'd be great. I'd love to ride
with you one day.
>> That's like the song
with nobody else but alone. You know,
>> I My friend Frasier, he kind of got me
into it. Bart got me into it. We just
kind of go, but most time I find myself
alone on it. Like you said, just just
thinking
>> it's meditative.
>> Yeah.
I don't know if you business here. This
is the logo of the to the channel.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> What do you think, Tiger?
>> I like it.
>> It fits.
>> Yeah. Fits just right.
>> I'll keep the bugs off. I'll put some
deed on it. God bless you, man.
>> All right, brother. Yeah.
>> Here. I hope you travel safe.
>> Yeah.
>> And I hope I appreciate you
>> bringing me up here.
>> Yeah. Thanks for trying to dig me out,
man. Hope you don't feel like I'm
running my mouth and showing off.
>> You're not at all.
>> You know,
>> just interesting things you're saying.
It was awesome. So, thank you.
>> Yeah, drive safe. Enjoy Cross Lake.
Okay, God bless you. Hope I see you
again.
>> The time has come and we've reached the
end of the main series. What an
incredible ride. What an amazing state.
What a cool state. I had no idea. It was
so interesting. And today, starting at
the base and ending up at Tiger's Place.
Thank you all in Maine who helped me
navigate your state, who got into my
videos, who told me where to go, and
thank you, the audience, for coming
along off to well, I'll keep it a
surprise where I'm off to next. Thanks
for coming along on that journey until
the next one.
Heat. Heat.
Ah, so cool.